What is humanity's greatest creation?
Correct, wine. But also incorrect
because wine was not created by man. It
was created by God. This God, Dionysus.
My favorite of the Greek gods for many
reasons, least of which, believe it or
not, being the wine. He is an
interesting creature, truly a
contradiction within himself and within
the larger Greek pantheon of gods. So,
it was only a matter of time before we
discussed him here under the fig tree.
And of course, the play by Euripides by
the same name, in which his madness
truly shines through. To everyone out
there today, especially my theater kids,
welcome home.
>> [music]
>> Dionysus is one of the oldest gods
attested in mainland Greek culture. The
earliest written records of the god come
from the Mycenaeans who predate the
ancient Greeks. Linear B tablets with
his name date to around 1300 BC. Take a
look at this one which was discovered in
Pylos. This is the name Diwonusu. That's
Dionysus. But the actual real cult of
Dionysus, which was a public civic
religion, became fully fledged in
antiquity, at which time devotees to the
god worshipped him in ecstasy. His cult,
which just to be clear in archaeologist
speak, is just a group of worshipers,
not like a Kool-Aid situation, involved
some old-time Greek mythology classics,
like satyrs and centaurs. Dionysus is
also friend to big cats everywhere. He's
constantly seen in the iconography
riding a leopard, wearing leopard skin,
or in a chariot drawn by panthers. And
holding this. This is a thyrsus, which
will become important later, and it's
essentially a large staff covered with
ivy vines and leaves and topped with
fennel.
Of course. This thing was carried around
during his festivals and religious
ceremonies. So, his second most famous
contribution to this mortal existence.
He taught humans how to cultivate grape
vines to create wine. And when they got
drunk, they were said to be ingesting
the god himself. Huh, that sounds
familiar. The term enthousiasmos, which
is the root for our modern English word
enthusiasm, meant to have the god inside
of you. And when that god was Dionysus,
it meant to have the wine inside of you
and to probably be wasted. And because
when you're drinking wine, you are
physically ingesting the god, when he is
inside of you, it is him, not the wine
itself, but him, that is altering your
perception, causing this drunkenness,
and freeing you momentarily from the
strict rules of society. This theme of
subversion and becoming something other
than yourself is so essential to
Dionysian worship. The man himself has
many names: Dionysus, Bacchus, Bromius,
etc. And that brings me to what I
believe is personally his most important
contribution, theater. One of the most
visible ways to worship Dionysus was to
perform. I'm doing it right now.
Theaters were constructed around Greece
and playwrights like Sophocles,
Aeschylus, Euripides, and Aristophanes
wrote plays that were performed at huge
festivals. We've talked about the Lenaia
before on this channel. It is, believe
it or not, a festival which is focused
around Dionysus and worshipping him. The
rural Lenaia began in the rural parts of
Attica and likely began as a way to
celebrate the cultivation of wines,
followed by dramatic performances. Then
there's the city Lenaia or the greater
Lenaia, which is the more interesting of
the two. These are more centered around
the city, taking place in Athens and
Eleusis, which likely began around the
6th century BC. They would go all out
for this one, sacrificing bulls,
carrying a huge wooden statue of
Dionysus around the city,
and of course, the dramatic competition.
Drama and performance is synonymous with
the way Dionysian ritual asks you to
behave. Dionysus is the god most closely
associated with a breakdown of stable
identities. Throughout his mythology, he
repeatedly dissolves distinctions
between the self and the other, between
male and female, mortal and divine,
civilization and wilderness. Anything
that involves worshipping him usually
involves disembodiment, some kind of
role reversal, ecstatic performances,
wearing masks, and some form of
collective participation or collective
frenzy. I don't know, have you guys ever
been on stage before? The very
mechanisms through which theater
operates are also central features of
Dionysian ritual because theater is
Dionysian ritual. Actors embody
different personas as a way to worship
the god because if they can do this
successfully, they achieve a type of
ecstasy and ecstasy is the ultimate goal
of Dionysian worship. Ecstasis, that's
where ecstasy comes from. It's emotion
to the extreme. The phenomenon of
feeling something so deeply and strongly
that you become outside of yourself.
Performance is a way to achieve this
because during a performance, you cannot
be yourself. That's the only that's the
only thing that's the only rule. Actors
would wear masks and attempt to reach
this point of disillusion with the self
to embody something else and that's the
form of ecstasy. Another way to reach
this ecstasy is just to go absolutely
mad. In Homer's hymn one, Dionysus is
given the epithet woman madner because
he made women mad in a crazy sense.
These mad women were known as maenads,
female followers of Dionysus who
performed ecstatic forms of worship
like dancing. This is a maenad. They
dressed typically in fawn skin and ivy
wreaths and they would run into the
forest and be imbued with enthusiasm
moss slash get drunk and call for
Dionysus. They could also get kind of
violent as don't worry, we we will be
going into detail about. Maenads would
catch kill wild animals like snakes or
bears or wolves while in the forest
during these ecstatic trances that they
would wind themselves up into. I think
this is very interesting because the
cult of Dionysus for women at this time
in ancient Greece probably would have
been quite appealing. Women were not
necessarily able to participate in a lot
of public life in ancient Greece like
drinking at the symposiums. That was
something that only men could do.
Hunting, that was something only men
could do. And women were often forced to
do the brunt of the domestic labor. But
participating in something like a
Dionysian ritual where you're with a
group of women and you're getting drunk
and going hunting and kind of getting
into this frenzy is again such a
subversion of the typical role that we
come to expect from ancient Greek
society. And you can understand how that
would be appealing for an oppressed
class at this time to occupy a more
dominant role. So like we said, Dionysus
likes to bend the gender, but he likes
to flip really every aspect of Greek
life on its head. This idea of ritual
frenzy is very interesting to me because
it sort of acted in ancient Greek
society as like a fail-safe. Like a
precaution, maybe I would say. People do
awful things. They kill each other. They
hurt each other. They have breaks in
their consciousness and in their
psychology. This is something that's
happened, my guess is since humans
stopped living in the wild, but I I
can't pinpoint it exactly. The ancient
Greeks knew this as well. They were
smart. Philosophers, guys. So by
creating something, by having something
like Dionysian ritual frenzy, ritual
madness, it's essentially creating a
structured, legal, and safe environment
where people can completely break the
rules of what is deemed a sophisticated,
proper society and just totally shatter
the social order, let loose,
and then go back to normal and keep
operating. Kind of like their version of
the purge, I guess. Ancient Greek
society was heavily restrictive. It was
very patriarchal. It was very
structured. They literally were so
insane that they invented democracy. So
you just imagine the levels of rigidity
these people would have had to be going
about their daily lives with. Plus,
women and slaves had virtually no
autonomy in this society. The cult of
Dionysus offers some freedom here. Women
could justifiably leave their homes.
They could head into the mountains, do
some dancing, get drunk with the girls.
Social classes completely vanished
during these Dionysic rituals. The rich
mingled with the poor. Everyone wore the
same clothes or swapped clothes around,
and people who were marginalized in this
society could assume high-status roles.
This essentially like comes in and
diffuses the pressure of this somewhat
oppressive society that, if not diffused
could lead to something horrible like
rebellion or chaos or collapse. And this
fits very cleanly into the ancient
Greeks idea of what is inside a human
brain. They thought that human nature
was fundamentally governed by two sides.
The rational often represented by Apollo
and the irrational often represented by
Dionysus. And you can't outright deny
the irrational side because that will
lead to you going actually crazy, having
a full psychotic break. You have to have
both of them. Like they both they're
there's there's two parts of humanity.
You can't deny one, but you can enclose
it. You can enclose it within ritual,
within specific dates and festivals that
would happen at specific times of the
year. Controlled chaos. This is
something else that theater achieves.
Maybe you've heard of it, it's called
catharsis. Aristotle coined this term to
essentially mean a purging of these
dangerous emotions that get built up in
humans over time. And when you have
opportunity to purge these emotions, you
can stay balanced and chill and cool.
When you're watching a play where
something awful is happening, you're
horrified and you're scared or you're
sad and you're crying and you're getting
out all of these emotions, but nothing
bad is actually happening to you. So you
can cathart them and then you're fine.
All forms of Dionysian ritual are trying
to get to the same thing. Ecstasy,
catharsis, and drunkenness, I guess. And
all of this that we've just talked about
forms part of typical Dionysian worship.
This is something that the general
public would be able to participate in
and certainly would at things like the
city Dionysia. Pretty much everyone
would be there. But what if your
devotion to the god is a little bit more
atypical? What if you're really goddamn
serious about Dionysus? Well, my friend,
that's what the mystery cult is for.
You have ordinary civic religion in
ancient Greece and then you have
something perhaps you haven't heard of
yet, mystery cults.
I'm going to put that down. If you're a
particularly mysterious, interesting,
chthonic god of the Greek pantheon, you
might have received a devout group of
followers who worships you a little bit
differently. Dionysus was one such god.
Demeter and Persephone were others. They
had a mystery cult that got so big that
Athens had to come and take over. But we
shan't be discussing them today. Today
we're talking about Bacchus. The
Dionysian mysteries, true to their name,
are quite mysterious because this was
not open to the public. One had to be
initiated into this cult in order to
form part of. And so we know a lot less
about what went on in these mysteries
and what the rituals entail. Lucky for
us, Euripides wrote a play about this
very topic. Now, to be fair, there's no
evidence that Euripides was part of the
Dionysian mysteries and I certainly I
don't think that he was. So we're going
to take his word in this play with a
grain of salt, okay? A grain of fennel,
of course. But I think given everything
we've just learned about Dionysus in
this teeny tiny little crash course,
it'll be fun to analyze the play and
perhaps see what Euripides can tell us
about this mysterious, contradictory
god. The play itself takes the form of
Dionysian worship. Yes, because it is a
play and meant to be performed and
therefore when this play was being
performed about Dionysus it was indirect
worship of Dionysus at the city
Dionysia. So Euripides is getting kind
of meta with it. This is one of his
later plays, so he was really breaking
the fourth wall, which didn't exist at
the time because they were open-air
theaters. But also within the structure
of the play, authority and gender and
social status are being upturned
completely. Dionysus is weird, okay?
He's a weirdo. He doesn't fit in.
Essentially in our play we are
confronted with two antagonists to each
other, Dionysus and Pentheus. Dionysus
is of course Dionysus and Pentheus is
the ruler of Thebes. And Dionysus comes
to Thebes and he's like, "I want you
guys to worship me." Pentheus
essentially is like, "I don't want to do
that." He wants to just watch, be a
spectator only. But that does not work
in Dionysian space and chaos ensues.
Worshiping Dionysus is a dangerous game.
Dionysian ritual logic demands
separation from the self. It demands a
dissolution of identity. And when
someone enters into that space, whether
it's willingly or not, they are changed
forever. Now that the backstory is out
of the way, shall we begin?
The play begins as most plays do, at the
start of the play. Today I'm using the
translation by William Arrowsmith
because I think it's a very accurate and
highly dramatic translation. But I do
want to say up front that there are a
lot of really beautiful translations of
this play. One of my personal favorites
is the Anne Carson translation. I think
it's perfect and beautiful and so is
she. She's a wonderful poet and I've
read a lot of her work. Due to her
background, I think her translation of
the play leans rather poetic, which I
think really complements what I believe
to be Euripides' most poetic play.
However, for the sake of accuracy,
because this is an overview, and for
many of you is likely your first
introduction to this play, I want to try
and stick as close as possible to the
traditional and the more widely
accredited translation, I suppose. But
if you come away from this video and you
really want to read the play for
yourself, which I always hope is what
you feel after watching one of these
videos, I would certainly recommend
picking up the Anne Carson translation.
I dare you to. And while we're on the
topic, because I've done a few of these
videos now, I do want to say that I
think to read something in its original
language, the language that it was
written in, is to understand it on a
much deeper level. I am forever grateful
to the translators for allowing these
ancient works of fiction to live on by
translating them into our modern
languages. But inevitably, with any
process of translation, something is
going to be lost, which is one of the
reasons why learning a language is so
uniquely valuable. You get to unlock an
entire new way of looking at the world,
a whole other level of perception. Now,
learning an entirely new language for
the sole purpose of achieving a deeper
understanding of a play or book is a
pretty difficult thing to do, especially
if you have commitments like living,
existing, etc. And this is coming from
someone who very nearly decided to study
linguistics instead of archaeology. And
because I think you and I are probably
quite like-minded, or at least I hope we
are, I have some great news. Today's
video is sponsored by Babbel. Babbel is
one of the top language learning apps in
the world and something that I truly
love about it is that 650 language
teachers were used to create the lessons
that you take. No AI, my friends. They
don't offer ancient Greek. I'm assuming
market research didn't come back super
promising on that one, but believe it or
not there are other languages to learn.
At the moment I'm using it to relearn
and keep alive my Italian, which I have
not spoken in years. Babbel is built to
teach you the conversations you would
actually have on a trip in a different
country. It's not just vocabulary lists.
It teaches you how to not look like a
tourist on the train, at a cafe, when
learning archaeological facts outside of
the context of a fig tree video essay.
Dionysus approved. One subscription
gives you access to all 14 languages
that Babbel offers. So, once I'm
perfectly fluent in Italian, I will be
moving on to German so that I can be
angry at Heinrich Schliemann in his
native language. Also, a subscription
gives you six logins to share or six
logins on all six of your burner phones.
No judgment. The link to that will be in
the description. Use the code FIG to get
20% off a lifetime subscription. If you
going somewhere this summer, start
learning the language now and please
tell me what language you've chosen to
learn. With the linguistic side of the
way,
shall we begin?
The very first words of the play are
spoken by the god himself. I'm Dionysus,
the son of Zeus, come back to Thebes,
this land where I was born. My mother
was Cadmus's daughter, Semele by name,
midwife by fire, delivered by the
lightning's blast. And here I stand, a
god incognito, disguised as man. There
before the palace, I see my
lightning-married mother's grave. And
there upon the ruins of her shattered
house, the living fire of Zeus still
smolders on in deathless witness of
Hera's violence and rage against my
mother. He has come to earth disguised
as a human so that he can return to
Thebes, his birthplace, where his mother
Semele was once a princess, and clearly
something went wrong. She was one of the
many mortal women that Zeus found
utterly irresistible. He came down from
Mount Olympus and had an affair with
Semele, which ended up with her being
pregnant with the god Dionysus. Hera,
Zeus's wife, obviously found out about
this. She's omnipresent. So, because
Semele is just a lame, low-life,
unimportant mortal, Hera is going to
find a way to get rid of her in the most
horrifying way possible. Aren't the gods
just so lovely? We should definitely
continue to worship them. What Hera does
is plant the seed of doubt in Semele's
mind about whether Zeus really loves
her. He's in love with you, but you
haven't even seen his true form. Some
boyfriend. And it's true, Semele has
never seen Zeus in his real, divine
form, because that would instantly kill
her. I guess she didn't know about that.
Semele asks Zeus to swear on the river
Styx that he will grant her one wish,
and Zeus obviously agrees. This is the
love of his month. He swears an
unbreakable oath that he will grant her
whatever wish she desires. And she
desires to see him in his true form. And
so, he has no choice. He has to grant
her this wish. So, he emerges from the
sky as a bolt of lightning, and just
looking at him, seeing him in all his
divine glory, burns Semele on the spot.
But recall, she is still pregnant. Zeus
comes back down to the ground and
manages to save his unborn son, taking
him out of the belly of the dying Semele
and stitching him into his thigh. So,
little fetus Dionysus is essentially
still gestating in Zeus's thigh until he
is born, Dionysus. Now, Semele's family,
royal shits, they did not believe that
she was in love with a god and that a
god was in love with her, and they told
the entirety of Thebes that she was
struck by lightning as punishment for
the fact that she lied about having a
baby with Zeus. They told everyone that
Semele was having an affair and that she
was pregnant with an illegitimate child,
and that the child she was carrying died
along with her. Semele's father and
sisters rejected Dionysus as their
grandson and nephew, and he was left
without a home. He goes on wandering for
many, many years. I won't tell you what
happened, but now he has returned to
Thebes to clear his mother's name and
punish his mother's family for the way
they treated her. Thebes is currently
being ruled by Pentheus. He's a dick. He
has explicitly forbidden the worship of
Dionysus in Thebes, which simply will
not do. This is the land of his family,
and they're not going to worship him.
I'm pretty sure that's illegal. Dionysus
is taking this very personally, and it
does seem quite personal, so I get it.
Do what you got to do. And what does he
got to do? He explains it to us. I have
come to refute that slander spoken by my
mother's sisters, those who least had
right to slander her. Because of that
offense, I have strung them with frenzy,
hounded them from home and up to the
mountains where they wander, crazed of
mind. There they sit, rich and poor
alike, beneath the silver firs of the
ruthless rocks. This city must learn its
lesson. It lacks initiation in my
mysteries, that I shall vindicate my
mother Semele and stand revealed to
mortal eyes as the god she bore to Zeus.
Mhm. Okay. So, naturally, he has
inflicted the minds of all of the women
of Thebes with some kind of Dionysic
madness. They've all fled to Mount
Cithaeron, where they now Maenads in
worship of Dionysus, sing and dance and
perform Bacchic rites, which were part
of the Dionysian mysteries. Now, to me
and you, this seems very compelling, and
I think that to an audience member
watching this play, this would also be
insanely compelling because chances are
this audience member is not part of the
Dionysian mysteries and would have had
no idea what goes on in them. So, they'd
be sitting in the theater like, "Oh my
god, we're going to learn the secrets?"
No. But, we are going to get Euripides'
creatively licensed retelling. By doing
this to the women of Thebes, Dionysus is
trying to prove that he is a powerful
god that must be worshipped. His rites
will be established in Thebes and then
in all of Greece, and at that point, he
will happily go on his way. He then
calls out to his ladies, his nomadic
cult of women followers who have
followed him throughout Anatolia, and
tells them to get this [__] going. On my
women, women who worship me, come and
with your native drum pound at the
palace doors of Pentheus. Let the city
of Thebes behold you while I return
among Cithaeron's forest glens where my
Bacchae wait and join their whirling
dances. And guess what? These ladies are
our beautiful, exultant, religiously
fanatic chorus. They enter from both
sides of the stage and sing a lovely ode
to our Dionysus, which ends in a call to
Thebes to worship the god and the
ecstasy that comes from being one of the
Bacchae. Out of the land of Asia, down
from holy Tmolus, speeding the service
of god from Bromius we come. Hard are
the labors of god, hard, but his service
is sweet. Sweet to serve, sweet to cry
Bacchus. And through their chant and
song, we hear a little bit of what it
must be like to form part of the
Dionysian mysteries. Blessed, blessed
are those who know the mysteries of the
god. Blessed is he who hallows his life
in worship of god. He whom the spirit of
god possesses, he who is one with those
who belong to the holy body of god.
Blessed are the dancers and those who
are purified, who dance on the hill in
the holy dance of god. Blessed are those
who wear the crown of the ivy of god.
Blessed, blessed are they. Dionysus is
their god. Okay. This play uses the
theatrical component of the chorus in a
pretty interesting way. Typically in
ancient Greek plays, the chorus is
pretty removed from the actual action of
the play itself. They're there to mainly
act as a form of exposition for the
audience or to narrate or move things
along. Nothing happens directly to them
or because of them, which in the world
of storytelling essentially means they
aren't even really a character. They're
a device. What my best friend Euripides
has done in this instance, in a time
where choruses were going a little bit
out of fashion in the theatrical world,
becoming a little bit too contrived for
late 5th century poets, he has actually
made them integral to the story itself.
They are the cult of Dionysus. Singing
and dancing was their way of worship and
that's what they're doing on stage. So
in this play the chorus gets to fulfill
its traditional purpose and contribute
to the larger narrative of the story.
And because so much of what happens in
this play is directly referencing the
Dionysian mysteries that so many in the
audience wouldn't have been a part of
the chorus is also used to describe to
the viewers and to the other characters
in the play the mysterious mysteries
from within. Like I said there's no
evidence that Euripides was ever part of
these mysteries. He was actually kind of
infamous for being a little bit of a
skeptic. His plays are frequently
discussing the questionable morality and
justice of the traditional Olympian
gods. Remember Medea when the gods
whisked her away to safety after she
just killed her children? That is
somewhat morally ambiguous. So I think
it's kind of unlikely that someone with
such deeply rationalist beliefs would
permanently bind themselves to an oath
of secrecy in a mystical esoteric cult.
And on the off chance that he was
somehow part of the mysteries he
definitely isn't going to be revealing
all of its secrets to the huge audience
at the City Dionysia. You could be
killed for doing something like that.
But what he is doing is using the
language of the secret cult in a very
poetic way if I do say so myself which
represents the incredible emotional and
spiritual power of Dionysus the very god
in whose theater this play is being
performed. I told you he gets meta with
it try not to think about it too hard or
do you've got nowhere to be for the next
30 minutes. He was really going all out
in his old age. This initial scene which
is more of a prologue than the first
real scene of the play sets us up for an
insane ride because Dionysus is speaking
directly to us the audience. We know his
secret. Remember he's come down to earth
disguised as a mortal human some guy
coming from Lydia with his group of
Dionysus worshipers. He's a foreigner
and a stranger and none of the
characters in the play know who he is
not even his chorus. For all they know
he's a devotee of Dionysus who has come
to Thebes to cause chaos.
Enter Tiresias friend of the channel. He
is an old blind prophet who lives in
Thebes. He walks in wearing fawn skin,
crowned with a ring of ivy on his head,
and finding his way with a thyrsus. He's
decked out in Dionysian worship garb.
"Ho there, who keeps the gates? Summon
Cadmus, who built the towers of our
Thebes. Go, someone. Say Tiresias wants
him. He will know what errand brings me.
That agreement, age with age, we made to
deck our wands, to dress in skins of
fawn, and crown our heads with ivy." He
calls for his old friend Cadmus, the
founder of Thebes and Pentheus's
grandfather. These two go way back. And
when they were younger, they made a pact
to don the fawn skins of Dionysus and go
up to Mount Cithaeron and worship him.
Clearly, Cadmus has switched up his tune
from when he disowned his dead daughter,
now that he knows that she was, in fact,
actually pregnant with this new
up-and-coming god, Dionysus. You live
and you learn. "My old friend, I knew it
must be you when I heard your summons,
for there's a wisdom in his voice that
makes the man of wisdom known. But here
I am, dressed in the costume of the god,
prepared to go. We must do honor to this
god, for he was born my daughter's son,
who has been revealed to men, the god
Dionysus." He is very excited about
running up that mountain. And as the two
old friends prance around in their fawn
skins and ivy wreaths, they start to
feel young again, able to
[clears throat] move freely as they did
in their youth, unburdened by old bones.
"I could dance night and day, untiringly
beating the earth with my thyrsus. And
how sweet it is to forget my old age. It
is the same with me. I too feel young,
young enough to dance." I want to whole
play about these guys. They asked
themselves whether they're going to be
the only men who go up and the dancers
on Mount Cithaeron, who so far are all
women. "Are we the only men who will
dance for Bacchus?"
They are all blind. Only we can see. Get
it?
Cuz he's blind. Here, take my arm. Link
my hand in yours. I am a man, nothing
more. I do not scoff at heaven. People
may say, "Aren't you ashamed at your age
going dancing, wreathing your head with
ivy?" Well, I am not ashamed. Did the
god declare that just the young or just
the old should dance? No, he desires his
honor from all mankind. Generationally
great lines coming out of these two. And
just as these cuties are about to dance
off stage, absolute buzzkill Pentheus
enters and is immediately so negative.
He's heard something about how all the
women in his city have fled their homes
and are up dancing on a mountain
worshipping a god he doesn't care for.
And instead of being cool about it, he's
actually very, very mad. He goes off
about how depraved and sexually
liberated the women of Thebes have
become. Reports reach me of some strange
mischief here. Stories of our women
leaving home to frisk in mock ecstasies
among the thickets on the mountain,
dancing in honor of the latest divinity,
a certain Dionysus, whoever he may be.
In their midst, stand bowls brimming
with wine. And then, one by one, the
women wander off to hidden nooks where
they serve the lusts of men. Priestesses
of Bacchus, they claim they are, but
it's really Aphrodite they adore.
>> What did you just call him?
>> So, he's a bit of a prude and he's
determined to bring the women of Thebes
back down to the city. But, that is
becoming increasingly harder, especially
now that this hot stranger has come to
town with a new group of bacchants
following him around. Pentheus says that
he will have any woman who's joined in
this chaos be hunted down like the
animals they are and trapped in iron
nets, even if that should be his own
mother. Dude,
weird. Then, he turns around and sees
Cadmus, his grandfather, and Tiresias
dressed up in their fawn skins. What?
But, this is incredible. Tiresias, the
seer, tricked out in a dappled fawn
skin. And you, you, my own grandfather,
playing at the bacchan with a wand. Sir,
I shrink to see your old age so foolish.
Shake that ivy off, grandfather. Now,
drop that wand. Drop it, I say. He is
clearly not fond of this new god and is
horrified that his own grandfather is,
in his eyes, debasing himself by
becoming one of the bacchants. He blames
Tiresias for influencing him, saying
that he, as a prophet, is just doing
this so he can legitimize another god
and have a way to make some more money
cuz now he can charge more people to
prophesize for that God. You can't talk
about Tiresias like that here, man.
You're going to make an enemy out of me.
Tiresias explains his view that the
people of Greece have Demeter, the God
of food, for solid nourishment. And now
they have been given Dionysus, the God
of wine, for liquid nourishment. Mankind
possesses two supreme blessings. First
of these is the goddess Demeter. It was
she who gave to man his nourishment of
grain. But after her, there came the son
of Semele, who matched her present by
inventing liquid wine as his gift to
man. I'll cheers to that. You're
absolutely right, Tiresias, and you
should not let the likes of Pentheus
silence you. He doesn't get it. We get
it though, don't we, guys? Tiresias then
explains the origin myth of Dionysus,
which I have graciously already done for
us. You're welcome. And he says that
Dionysus will be revered and worshipped
throughout Greece, and Pentheus will
come to regret the level of disrespect
that he's showing to the God right now.
He is quite literally a prophet, so I
would trust his judgment, but I make
good decisions. That's why I'll never
hold a position of power. Do not be so
certain that power is what matters in
the life of man. Do not mistake for
wisdom the fantasies of your sick mind.
Welcome the God to Thebes. Crown your
head. Pour him libation and join his
revels. Cadmus and I, whom you ridicule,
will crown our heads with ivy and join
the dances of the God. An ancient
foolish pair, perhaps, but dance we
must. Nothing you have said would make
me change my mind or flout the will of
heaven. You are mad, grievously mad,
beyond the power of any drugs to cure,
for you are drugged with madness. Hm,
very interesting that Tiresias would end
his little tirade by calling Pentheus
mad. Madness, as we'll come to see, is
one of the main themes of this play,
thanks to the mad lad himself, Dionysus.
Tiresias says that the complete rigidity
that Pentheus is clinging to is in
itself a form of madness. Remember how
we said you have to get a little bit
crazy so that you don't go fully crazy?
Pentheus won't even let himself get a
little bit crazy, so I wonder how his
story's going to turn out. Cadmus tries
to put the crown of ivy on his
grandson's head, but he's like, "Well,
bro, don't touch me. Do not get your
crazy on me." The argument kind of gets
to a point where they just end up going
back and forth calling each other mad.
And Pentheus turns to his guys and is
like, "Go trash this man's house." Cool,
very mature, bro. Oh, and also, he's
decided he is going to kill this
stranger. Go scour the city for that
effeminate stranger, the man who infects
our women with this strange disease and
pollutes our beds. And when you take
him, clap him in chains and march him
here. He shall die as he deserves by
being stoned to death. Jesus Christ. The
two best friends realize that there is
no saving Pentheus, and they leave him
to his own self-inflicted destruction.
Reckless fool, you do not know the
consequences of your words. You talked
madness before, but this is raving
lunacy. Cadmus, let us go and pray for
this raving fool and for this city, too.
Pray to the god that no awful vengeance
strike from heaven. Take your staff and
follow me. Support me with your hands,
and I shall help you, too.
Bye, my lovelies. I miss you. Our chorus
come back to close out scene number one,
and they're singing about their
[__] I'm just kidding. It's a very
beautiful song in which they call upon a
goddess to look at how blasphemous
Pentheus is being and saying that he's
so obsessed with his own power that he
would denounce a literal god. They then
go on to say that as worshipers of
Dionysus, they wish that they could run
away from the city and go to Cyprus, the
isle of Aphrodite, where they would be
free to carry out their rights in peace.
But alas, they're not done with the city
yet. They still have to get everyone
singing and dancing and engaging in
dangerous levels of religious ecstasy.
Which I know by the way I've been
describing it so far sounds really fun
and exciting and cool. Allow me not to
get too carried away. This is a group of
religious fanatics that we're looking at
here. And Pentheus, especially in the
eyes of the audience of the time, would
have had reason for initially reacting
the way that he does. He is the leader
of the city, and all of a sudden all of
the women in the city have just run away
and gone up to a mountain, and they seem
to be crazed and dancing. Like, yeah, he
should he should be worried, I guess.
And Tiresias and Cadmus both end up
following the god for kind of shallow
reasons. Their desire to follow the
Maenads up the mountain comes from a
place of fear. They want to stay young.
When they start dancing, they feel young
again. They don't want to grow old. They
don't want to have the punishment of the
god. Whether or not they actually truly
adore him is secondary to their desire
for self-preservation. So, Pentheus
isn't completely in the wrong, he but he
is mostly in the wrong. He does
immediately have this preoccupation with
sex and the sexual proclivities that
these women are engaging in and immense
hatred for their level of drunkenness
and freedom. Which they're mainly up
there singing and dancing. I don't know
why he's got to be weird about it. So,
while Pentheus maybe it does have a
right to be worried, the play eventually
firmly positions him as this rigid
authoritarian figure. And the chorus
essentially acts as a more balanced
nuanced take.
In the next scene, Dionysus, ala
stranger disguise, is led onto stage by
Pentheus's men, captured. And it was
actually really super easy to do. He
just gave himself up willingly. And now
he's in front of Pentheus just smiling
and having a blast. He is way too cool,
calm, and collected. And Pentheus is
unnerved by that and gets up all in his
face trying to suss him out. You are
attractive stranger, at least to women,
which explains I think your presence
here in Thebes. Your curls are long, you
do not wrestle I take it. And what fair
skin you have, you must take care of it.
daylight complexion. No, it comes from
the night when you hunt Aphrodite with
your beauty. Obsessed obsessed with that
description but okay
we go on. This scene is really
wonderful. The two have a very
Euripidean battle of wits and it's so
fun. And throughout the scene, the
prisoner, Dionysus or the stranger,
takes the upper hand over this figure of
authority. And he really doesn't have to
try too hard. He's just so charming.
Even Pentheus's cronies when they were
trying to capture him were like, "Sorry,
man. You seem really cool but my boss
just really wants me to take you to him
in chains." Dionysus answers all of
Pentheus's questions with striking
honesty, which just makes Pentheus more
dumbfounded and confused. Now then, "Who
are you and from where?" "My country is
Lydia. Who is this god whose worship you
have imported into Hellas? Dionysus, the
son of Zeus. He initiated me. You have
some local Zeus who spawns new gods? He
is the same as yours, the Zeus who
married Semele. But more so than his
confusion, Pentheus can't help but be
intrigued. He so badly wants to know
what happens in the mysteries that this
stranger has brought to Thebes. Tell me
the benefits that those who know your
mysteries enjoy. I am forbidden to say.
But they are worth knowing. Your answers
are designed to make me curious. No. Our
mysteries abhor an unbelieving man. You
say you saw the god. What form did he
assume? Whatever form he wished. The
choice was his, not mine. But he is
Dionysus. And we know that, obviously,
the audience. But Pentheus doesn't.
Isn't this fun, guys? I love knowing
everything. And Pentheus is kind of
stuck now because he's trying to mock
this stranger, but he doesn't even know
what the rights that he's performing
are, cuz he's not part of them. Oh my
god, the FOMO would be eating me alive.
Dionysus is like, all right, look, you
got me here. What are you going to do
with me? First of all, I shall cut off
your girlish curls. My hair is holy. My
curls belong to god. Pentheus shaves
away the god's curls. Second, you will
surrender your wand. You take it. It
belongs to Dionysus. Pentheus takes the
thyrsus. Last, I shall place you under
guard and confine you in the palace. The
god himself will set me free whenever I
wish. He is here now and sees what I
endure from you. Where is he? I cannot
see him. With me. Your blasphemies have
made you blind. You just have to love.
Pentheus throws a little hissy fit and
is like, stop making fun of me. The
stranger is like, no, dude, for real,
Dionysus is here, I promise. You just
can't see him cuz you're not pure of
heart. Cuz he is Dionysus. Pentheus has
had enough. He tells his attendants to
tie up the stranger. And as they do, the
chorus come in chanting louder and
louder until Pentheus gets fed up and
leaves saying that he will take all of
these women and sell them as slaves or
make them work for him. As Dionysus, the
stranger, is being led off stage in
chains, he says simply, Dionysus, whom
you outrage by your acts, who you deny
as god, will call you to account. When
you set chains on me, you manacle the
god."
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> The chorus close out our scene with a
cry, lamenting their imprisonment. "Oh
Dionysus, do you see how in shackles we
are held unbreakable in the bonds of
oppressors? Descend from Olympus, Lord.
Come, wield your wand of gold and quell
with death this beast of blood whose
violence abuses man and god
outrageously." Just then, thunder and
lightning ripples through the sky and
the chorus fall to the ground. Their
cries are directly answered by the god
in
"What, women of Asia, were you so
overcome with fright you fell to the
ground? I think then you must have seen
how Bacchus jostled the palace of
Pentheus. But come, rise. Do not be
afraid." Cue applause. Dionysus
essentially caused an earthquake and the
chorus have an interesting moment here
where they see Dionysus both as a deity
and in his disguise as this mortal man
as one. As if the god has inhabited the
body of their earthly leader and is
acting as both. They are showing us this
contradiction that Dionysus can be.
Remember this idea of enthusiasm moss
when you have the god inside of you. So,
they can believe that they are
witnessing both a mortal man and a true
divine form in and of the same body. "Oh
greatest light of our holy revels, how
glad I am to see your face. Without you,
I was lost." All you need is a lot of
faith and a little bit of cognitive
dissonance. This moment of blurred lines
only lasts for a second though and they
start asking their leader how he could
have possibly escaped from Pentheus'
guards. And he's like, "With really no
problem at all. That was easy and fun,
too. Let me tell you the story. With
ease. No effort was required. But the
manacles on your wrists?" He seemed to
think that he was chaining me, but never
once so much as touched my hands. He fed
on his desires. Inside the stable he
intended as my jail, instead of me he
found a bull and tried to rope its knees
and hooves. But at that moment, Bacchus
came, shook the palace and touched his
mother's grave with tongues of fire.
Imagining the palace was in flames,
Pentheus went rushing here and there,
shouting to his slaves to bring him
water. Every hand was put to work, in
vain. Bursting in, Pentheus thrust and
stabbed at that thing of gleaming air as
though he thought it me. And then, once
again, the god humiliated him. At that
bitter sight, Pentheus dropped his
sword, exhausted by the struggle. A man,
a man and nothing more. Yet he presumed
to wage a war with god. Dionysus went
full mental warfare on this man, making
him see things that weren't really
there, having him stab shadows on the
walls, and put out imaginary fires. Just
humiliating. But Pentheus is resilient
cuz he's back for round two. He enters
the scene and spots the stranger. You,
well, what do you have to say for
yourself? How did you escape? Answer me.
Your anger walks too heavily.
Tread lightly here.
Pentheus is so out of his depth, bro.
Dionysus tells him, "I told you someone
would free me if you locked me up." And
Pentheus is like, "Yeah, okay, real
funny. Who freed you?" He who makes the
grape grow its clusters for mankind. A
splendid contribution that. You
disparage the gift that is his chiefest
glory. If I catch him here, he will not
escape my anger. I shall order every
gate and every tower to be bolted tight.
And so, could not a god hurdle your city
walls? Before Dionysus can prove yet
again that he is the more intelligent of
the two, a messenger comes with news
from Mount Cithaeron. You know, the
mountain where all the women are singing
and dancing and drinking. Pentheus, king
of Thebes, I come from Cithaeron where
the gleaming flakes of snow fall on and
on forever. Get to the point. What is
your message, man? Rude. He's like,
okay, don't shoot the messenger,
literally, please. I know how you can
get, king. You're a bit temperamental.
Pentheus is like, all right, all right,
all right. I won't shoot you. Tell me,
what are the women doing on the
mountain? So, the messenger explains
that he saw three groups of women,
including Semele's sisters and
Pentheus's own mother, Agave, sleeping
peacefully up in the mountain air. They
didn't seem to be drunk or out of their
minds at all. They were enjoying nature.
And when the sun rose, first they let
their hair fall loose down over their
shoulders and fastened their skins of
fawn with rising snakes that licked
their cheeks. Breast swollen with milk,
new mothers who had left their babies
behind at home and nestled gazelles and
young wolves in their arms suckling
them. One woman struck her thyrsus
against a rock and a fountain of cool
water came bubbling up. Another drove
her fennel in the ground and where it
struck the earth at the touch of God a
spring of wine poured out. Those who
wanted milk scratched the soil with bare
fingers and the white milk came welling
up. Pure honey spurted streaming from
their wands. If you had been there and
seen these wonders for yourself, you
would have gone down on your knees and
prayed to the God you now deny. It's
magic, bro. You don't get it. The
messenger says that he and the other
shepherds that were on the mountain were
marveling over what they saw. Like this
beautiful scene of literal magic. Um and
then they thought, "Hey, why don't we
kidnap one and bring it back to our king
so that maybe he'll like us and he'll
give us kiss." They decide to ambush
Agaue, Pentheus' mother. And they hide
in the undergrowth ready to take her
when the moment arises. Oh, but it
doesn't though because they are then
found by the rest of the women and
they're pissed. Leaping up I tried to
seize her, but she gave a cry. "Hounds
who run with me, men are hunting us
down. Follow, follow me. Use your wands
for weapons." At this we fled and barely
missed being torn to pieces by the
women. Unarmed they swooped down upon
the herds of cattle grazing there on the
green of the meadow. And then you could
have seen a single woman with bare hands
tear a fat calf in two while others
clawed the heifers to pieces. They tore
into these shepherds' herd with absolute
frenzy and literally tore the cattle to
pieces. The messenger is horrified by
what he saw now and is like, "Dude, what
my herd is all gone. Please welcome
Dionysus into this city so that this can
stop. He is clearly a powerful God and
should be feared and respected. Whoever
this God may be, sire, welcome him to
Thebes for he is great in many other
ways as well. It was he, or so they say,
who gave to mortal men the gift of
lovely wine, by which our suffering is
stopped. And if there is no god of wine,
there is no love, no Aphrodite either,
nor other pleasure left to men. The
messenger leaves, and finally Pentheus
is convinced of the true power of
Dionysus. Psych, of course he's not. He
ignores this warning, too. And he
decides that these women up on the
mountain are clearly clinically insane
and way too dangerous to keep around. Um
So, he's going to kill every single one
of them, which I would like to remind
you is every single woman in Thebes.
Absolute freak behavior. So, he rallies
his troops to take up arms against the
Bacchae. Dionysus says, "There is no way
you're going to do that, my friend. If
you offer the god a sacrifice, though,
he may be willing to forgive you."
Nudge, nudge, wink, wink. That's between
you and me. And Pentheus is like, "Oh,
yeah, I tend to make a sacrifice up on
Mount Cithaeron of all those women." All
right, no, no, no. Change tactic.
Dionysus is like, "All right, I'll lead
the women back to Thebes." Um and
Pentheus is like, "Mm, no, that sounds
like a scam. I'm off." Wait, would you
like to see the rebels on the mountain?
Well, now you've piqued my interest. For
as much as he claims to be horrified and
disgusted by what is happening on the
mountain, Pentheus is far, far more
curious. He's fascinated, in fact. So,
he agrees.
We got him. Dionysus says that in order
to not be torn apart like that herd of
cattle and very nearly their men,
Pentheus will have to go up the mountain
in disguise. First, however, you must
dress yourself in women's clothes. What?
You want me, a man, to wear a woman's
dress? But why? If they knew you were a
man, they would kill you instantly. I
shall go inside with you and help you
dress. Dress? In a woman's dress, you
mean? I would die of shame. Very well.
Then you no longer hanker to see the
Maenads.
What is this costume I must wear? He
keeps up the pretense in this scene a
little bit of being like, "Who, me? I
could never. Well, well, I could never
wear a dress." But Dionysus already
knows that he's got him. Pentheus exits
to go get in disguise and Dionysus turns
to his chorus. Women are prey now
thrashers in the net we threw. He shall
see the Bacchae and pay the price with
death. Yay! The chorus responds in my
favorite of their interludes where they
imagine life as a deer running through
the forest finally free from a hunter.
They sing about escape and their
discovery that wisdom, true wisdom, this
gift that the gods gave humanity is
divine revenge. And I think it's very
beautiful so I will read a bit to you
now. When I shall dance once more with
bare feet the all night dances, tossing
my head for joy in the damp air, in the
dew, as a running fawn might frisk for
the green joy of the wide fields,
free from fear of the hunt, free from
the circling beaters and the nets of
woven mesh and the hunters hallooing on
their yelping packs, bounding over the
marsh, leaping to frisk, leaping for
joy, gay with the green of the leaves to
dance for joy in the forest, to dance
where the darkness is deepest, where no
man is. What is wisdom? What gift of the
gods is held in honor like this? To hold
your hand victorious over the heads of
those you hate?
Honor is precious forever.
Scene four starts with Dionysus on
stage. He calls out to Pentheus. He's
like, "Get up you crazy kid, let's
dance." Pentheus enters wearing a long
linen dress carrying a thyrsus with fawn
skins draped over him and on his head is
a gorgeous wig of blond curls. And he's
acting different. I seem to see two suns
blazing in the heavens and now two
Thebes, two cities and each with seven
gates and you, you are a bull who walks
before me there. Horns have sprouted
from your head. Have you always been a
beast? He's a little dazed. I think
Dionysus got to him, if you know what I
mean. It is the god you see. You see
what you could not when you were blind.
Pentheus has been enraptured by Dionysus
and is pliant under his words, doing
whatever he says and making a little bit
of a fool of himself in front of us, the
audience. We have a few laughs, but then
we get serious. Because while Pentheus
is acting silly and asking Dionysus if
he looks pretty, Dionysus is answering
in what seems like nice, kind of
innocuous ways. But guys, never forget
that everything is actually that deep.
In fact, it's usually much deeper. And
while Pentheus is imagining that he will
return home from Mount Cithaeron a hero,
celebrated and carried in his mother's
arms to be an example for all the men of
Thebes, well, he's not wrong, but fate
has a funny way of twisting words. Then
lead me through the very heart of
Thebes, since I alone of all this city
dare to go. A great ordeal awaits you,
but you are worthy of your fate. I shall
lead you safely there. Someone else
shall bring you back.
Yes, my mother, an example to all men.
You'll be carried home cradled in your
mother's arms. You will spoil me. I mean
to spoil you. Ooh. Oh my god. Oh my god.
Oh my god. In this last scene between
Pentheus and Dionysus, we have the
complete shift of our once uptight,
rigid King Pentheus. And as Pentheus is
led out of his mind and dressed up like
a little sacrificial lamb up Mount
Cithaeron, the chorus sings to us once
more. Run to the mountain, fleet hounds
of madness. Run, run to the revels of
Cadmus's daughters. His mother shall see
him first. She will cry to the Maenads,
"Who is the spy who has come to the
mountains to peer at the mountain revels
of the women of Thebes? What bore him,
Bacchae? This man was born of no woman.
Oh, Dionysus, reveal yourself a bull, be
manifest a snake with darting heads, a
lion breathing fire. Cast your noose
about this man who hunts your Bacchae.
Bring him down, trampled under foot by
the murderous herd of your Maenads."
This chant is dripping with vengeance.
The chorus call on the hounds of madness
to seize the Maenads up on Mount
Cithaeron so that they can kill Pentheus
when he reaches them. They sing of his
impiety and the dangers of failing to
worship and respect a god. The chorus
summoned Dionysus in all of his many
forms and they demand the blood of
Pentheus.
A messenger enters from Mount Cithaeron
to recount for us the death of Pentheus.
The chorus called for his gruesome
murder and that is exactly what they got
and they're pretty psyched. The
messenger is like, "Guys, you're acting
really excited about someone being
ripped to shreds. It's kind of creepy."
And they're like, "Haha, yeah, tell us
how it happened." And so he does. The
messenger recounts the story of himself,
Pentheus and Dionysus about how they
climbed up the mountain to see the
revels of the women and they saw the
Maenads sitting peacefully under the fir
trees. Dionysus then like grabs a tree
down and puts Pentheus in it and like
slingshots it back up so that he becomes
visible all of a sudden to all the
women. And as soon as they see him, a
voice from the sky, Dionysus obviously,
tells them, "Hey, this man is mocking
you. He's an intruder." Oh my god. Oh my
god. Led by Agave, Pentheus' own mother,
the Maenads attack. And breaking loose
like startled doves through grove and
torrent over jagged rocks they flew.
Their feet maddened by the breath of
god. Thousands of hands tore the fir
tree from the earth and down, down from
his high perch fell Pentheus. Tumbling
to the ground, sobbing and screaming as
he fell for he knew his end was near.
His own mother, like a priestess with
her victim, fell upon him first. "No, no
mother, I am Pentheus, your own son, the
child you bore to Echion. Pity me, spare
me mother. I have done a wrong but do
not kill your own son for my offense."
But she was foaming at the mouth and her
crazed eyes rolling with frenzy. She was
mad, stark mad, possessed by Bacchus.
Ignoring his cries of pity, she seized
his left arm at the wrist then planting
her foot upon his chest, she pulled,
wrenching away the arm at the shoulder.
Not by her own strength for the god had
put inhuman power in her hands.
Together, the Maenads pull Pentheus limb
from limb. One tore off an arm, another
a foot, still warm in its shoe. His ribs
were clawed clean of flesh, and every
hand was smeared with blood as they
played ball with scraps of Pentheus'
body. His mother, picking up his head,
impaled it on her wand. She seems to
think it is some mountain lion's head,
which she carries in triumph through the
thick of Cithaeron. But all the victory
she carries home is her own grief.
That's what happens when you mess with
Dionysus, friends. The last thing that
Pentheus does in his wasted life is
reach out to his mother and beg her not
to kill him. And it is then, when his
own mother cannot recognize the face of
her son, that he realizes how powerful
Dionysus really is. But it is much too
little, much too late. Agave runs
towards the palace, still possessed by
the god. She holds her son's head in her
arms, thinking it's the head of a lion
she killed in a a brilliant hunt. She
talks to the chorus about how wonderful
her and the Maenads were. Happy was the
hunting, she repeats over and over
again. And the chorus look at her with
pity. Cadmus, her father and Pentheus'
grand- father, come and he's carrying
with him the rest of Pentheus' remains.
Then the most sickening part of the
entire play, I think. Cadmus looks his
daughter in the eyes and slowly takes
her out of this frenzy and brings her
back to herself. First, raise your eyes
to the heavens. There. But why? Does it
look the same as it did, or has it
changed? It seems somehow clearer,
brighter than it was before. Can you
answer clearly? Can you still hear me?
What was the name of the child you bore
your husband? Pentheus. And whose head
do you hold in your hands? A lion's
head. Or so the huntress told me. Look
directly at it. Just a quick glance.
What is it? What am I holding in my
hands? Look more closely still. Study it
carefully. No. Oh, gods. I see the
greatest grief there is. Is that not the
most horrifying thing you've ever heard?
Really big what's in the box energy. At
this point in the play, there's There's
a pretty big chunk of the text missing.
We don't actually know what happened in
these next few lines, but when the
fragments pick back up, Agave is trying
to put the pieces of Pentheus back
together. This is where Dionysus reveals
himself as a god for the first time in
the entire play. In lines that echo his
very first, "I am Dionysus, the son of
Zeus returned to Thebes, revealed a god
to men. But the men of Thebes blasphemed
me. They slandered me. They said I came
of mortal man." He gives us a little bit
of an epilogue where he tells us exactly
how this wretched family that blasphemed
him and mistreated his mother will spend
the rest of their lives. Agave will be
banished from Thebes, naturally. And
just for shits and giggles, both Cadmus
and his wife will be turned into snakes
that will travel with barbarian hordes
and invade Greek lands. I don't know,
man, but that doesn't sound good, does
it? Cadmus tried to plead with the god
for a lighter sentence, and Dionysus
responds with one of my favorite lines
from the entire play. "We implore you,
Dionysus. We have done wrong, but your
sentence is too harsh." "Too late. When
there was time, you did not know me."
Chills.
Chills. Father and daughter, Agave and
Cadmus, say goodbye to each other, and
so the play ends. Even though those two
barely appear in the play itself, this
is their tragedy. It's a family tragedy,
and it's the way that Cadmus's family
was brought down due to his mistreatment
of Dionysus's mother. The ones who
suffer the most are ones that actually
worship Dionysus. Agave and Cadmus both
went up to Mount Cithaeron. So really, I
think Dionysus was more pissed about his
mom being treated badly than about
anyone who didn't worship him. Pentheus
got to die. Cadmus and Agave have to
live with this forever. And that, my
friends, was The Bacchae. While I'm not
convinced that it shows us the true
nature of the Dionysian mysteries, it is
an incredible play which truly, while
you're reading it, you have so much fun
because Dionysus is just really getting
to show off how fun and witty he is. And
then at the end, you are subjected to
one of the most horrible scenes I've
ever read. And it's actually quite
interesting because in most ancient
Greek plays, like a few that we have
read together here, the really horrible
gruesome stuff happens off screen. A
messenger will come in, like when
Oedipus gouged out his own eyes, a
messenger comes in and tells us. And
even in this play, a messenger comes in
and tells us about how Pentheus was
ripped limb from limb. But then at the
very end, we actually bear witness to
Agave bringing her child's head back to
Thebes. And her reaction after realizing
that it's her son, oh my god. You see
that live in real time on the stage.
Lord, this play is Pentheus
demonstrating to us the logic of
Dionysian ritual, whether it's public or
part of the mystery cults, is
fundamentally transformative. You are
forever changed after coming into
contact with this god and after
achieving the ecstasy that Dionysian
ritual demands of you. And it does
demand it. Dionysian ritual space
requires your participation. You can't
be a spectator. Pentheus wanted to go up
to the mountain and just watch what the
women were doing, but how did that work
out for him? Truly a beautiful beautiful
play and um I'm glad we could share it
together. Have a beautiful rest of your
summer/winter. Much love and don't
forget to go get drunk tonight so
Dionysus doesn't get his women to tear
you to pieces. Unless you're into that.
Bye, love you.